<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-24T17:30:06+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">nikki’s notebook</title><subtitle>to drop everthing</subtitle><entry><title type="html">After reading Fountainhead</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/after-reading-fountainhead" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="After reading Fountainhead" /><published>2024-05-04T08:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-05-04T08:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/after-reading-fountainhead</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/after-reading-fountainhead"><![CDATA[<p>There are a lot of thoughts after reading The Fountainhead.</p>

<h2 id="be-true-to-yourself-you-are-the-one-most-easily-fooled">Be true to yourself, you are the one most easily fooled</h2>

<p>Be a person of integrity. Only then will you avoid living as a second-hander, needing no external approval. The most valuable thing on earth can only be obtained from within yourself. In Ayn Rand’s time, newspapers could shape public opinion, much like social media and algorithms manipulate people’s thoughts today. You may think it’s your opinion, but it’s often fed by big data. It’s harder now to be honest with yourself – to truly mean what you say and do what you want, rather than plagiarizing others’ ideas.
Almost every character in the novel or movie, as long as they are honest and true to their deepest choices, whether good or evil, becomes lovable. Holding your opinion strongly and acting according to your principles defines integrity; otherwise, you can only be a fraud.</p>

<h2 id="talent-human-intelligence">Talent, human intelligence</h2>

<p>Especially in modern society, we impose too much moral judgment on individuals and stress the importance of teamwork. But that’s just an alibi found by the incapable – it’s not true commitment.
A building can only be erected according to one person’s vision; others merely implement it. Any modification or compromise weakens the greatness of the original concept. The same applies to other human endeavors; there can only be one driving force. No great work arises from brainstorming, collecting user feedback, or constant compromising. Traditional teamwork leads only to mediocrity. Those who claim cooperation is vital usually need it to disguise their own inadequacies. True talent is rare, and we need more tolerance for the truly talented and boldly original minds. Still, I believe history is written by a few great people, and the rest of us are fortunate to enjoy the world shaped by these great minds.</p>

<h2 id="self-sufficient-and-unconditional-self-love">Self-sufficient and unconditional self-love</h2>

<p>At the core of positive traits like confidence and a positive attitude lies self-love and self-sufficiency. Far from selfishness, this grants the courage to love others. Outwardly manifesting as different traits, underneath lies a strong foundation of needing nothing, requiring no external approval – being secure in oneself.
“I couldn’t live for you, but I can die for you” – friendship based on attraction rather than need is the true friendship sought.</p>

<p>I think I encountered The Fountainhead at the right time.
You may feel conflicted for holding perspectives that contradict social norms, but those books with characters resonating with you, remind you you’re not alone – others think the same way, giving you courage to embrace those perspectives authentically.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There are a lot of thoughts after reading The Fountainhead.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts about the coming New Year</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/thoughts-about-the-coming-new-year" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts about the coming New Year" /><published>2024-04-01T08:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-04-01T08:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/thoughts-about-the-coming-new-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/thoughts-about-the-coming-new-year"><![CDATA[<p>Things have changed a bit this year.</p>

<p>As the Chinese New Year approached, everyone around me kept asking when I was going to go back home. It struck me as a bit odd because Shanghai now feels more like home to me.</p>

<p>Why does everyone assume that your home is where you were born - a place you can always return to? Can you really find the most comfort there? Do you feel most rejuvenated and safe when you’re there? No, I’m afraid that’s not the case for most people. Or perhaps most people haven’t really considered this question and just go by the habit that yes, of course, that’s where I’m from, and that’s where my family lives, so it must be home.</p>

<p>For me, that’s not the case at all. In fact, I’ve long noticed that I’m often more miserable when I’m back “home” than when I’m outside that area. Before, I would feel guilty about this, due to the moral reasoning I was taught growing up - that it’s the natural and right thing to do to stick with your family and always come back.</p>

<p>But no, you can choose wherever you want to be as long as you feel good. And if anything bugs you and you don’t think it’s worth your energy to fight back, you can simply stay away.</p>

<p>Sure, there must be some people who were born into a happy family and feel safe staying there. But for those who don’t have that, it’s necessary to find somewhere you truly feel you belong. It’s hard, but you have no choice. You are not doomed to be miserable where you came from - the whole world is waiting for you.</p>

<p>Another thing I find strange is that as the festival approaches, everything just seems to slow down. But it’s not a good kind of slow down. It feels more like people are living a hard daily life and finally find an excuse to not worry about the trivialities, to find a cover to hide behind - “Oh, everything that’s bothering me will be resolved after the festival.” “Now it’s holiday time, and we should all just chill out without thinking about anything else.”</p>

<p>But why? If the holiday time is when you feel most blessed, why can’t you just live every day like that?</p>

<p>I suppose we all grow up in a culture of always waiting for something better to happen. Life has been divided into different periods, with different tasks assigned to each. People make you believe that once you’ve gotten through a specific period, the difficulties will resolve - like when you were in primary school, the task was to get into a good middle school, then high school, choose a good college major, get a decent job. And then they’ll expect you to get married, have a child, and then what? You’re always waiting for the next thing to happen, always thinking that if that thing happens, everything will be fine and all problems will be solved.</p>

<p>Festivals exist for this reason - to create some ruptures in your life, to destroy the consistency of it. They make you feel this is a period where you can indulge yourself, and after it’s over, you’ll go back to your daily life. So now you have two versions of life - the normal, burdened daily grind, and your idealized version. No! If you want something, get it now. If you enjoy a certain lifestyle, just live that way!</p>

<p>These insights may seem banal, but it took me years and many reflections to finally realize them and be able to live by them without fear.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Things have changed a bit this year.]]></summary></entry></feed>